<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-dnssec-automation-latest"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  tocInclude="true"
  tocDepth="4"
  symRefs="true"
  sortRefs="true"
  version="3">

	<!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

	<front>
		<title abbrev="DNSSEC automation">DNSSEC automation</title>

		<author fullname="Ulrich Wisser" initials="U" surname="Wisser">
			<address>
				<email>ulrich@wisser.se</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<author fullname="Shumon Huque" initials="S" surname="Huque">
			<organization>Salesforce</organization>
			<address>
				<email>shuque@gmail.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<author fullname="Johan Stenstam" initials="J" surname="Stenstam">
			<organization>The Swedish Internet Foundation</organization>
			<address>
				<email>johan.stenstam@internetstiftelsen.se</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date day="4" month="4" year="2024"/>

		<area>Operations and Management Area</area>
		<workgroup>Domain Name System Operations (dnsop)</workgroup>

		<keyword>DNS</keyword>
		<keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
		<keyword>Multi-Signer</keyword>
		<keyword>Automation</keyword>

		<abstract>
			<t>
				This document describes an algorithm and protocol to
				automate the setup, operations, and decomissioning of
				<xref target="RFC8901">Multi-Signer DNSSEC</xref>
				configurations. It employs Model 2 of the multi-signer
				specification, where each operator has their own distinct
				KSK and ZSK sets (or CSK sets),
				<xref target="RFC8078">Managing DS Records from the Parent via
				CDS/CDNSKEY</xref>, and <xref target="RFC7477">Child-to-Parent
				Synchronization in DNS</xref> to accomplish this.
			</t>
		</abstract>

		<note removeInRFC="true">
		<name>Discussion Venues</name>
		<t>
			Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at
			<eref target="https://github.com/ietf-wg-dnsop/draft-ietf-dnsop-dnssec-automation"/>.
		</t>
		</note>

	</front>
	<middle>
		<section numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>Introduction</name>
			<t>
				<xref target="RFC8901" /> describes the necessary steps and API for a
				multi-signer DNSSEC configuration. In this document we will combine
				<xref target="RFC8901" /> with <xref target="RFC8078" /> and
				<xref target="RFC7477" /> to define an automatable algorithm for
				setting up, operating and decomissioning of a multi-signer
				DNSSEC configuration.
			</t>
			<t>
				One of the special cases of multi-signer DNSSEC is the secure
				change of DNS operator. Using multi-signer Model 2 the secure change
				of DNS operator can be accomplished.
			</t>
			<section numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>Out-Of-Scope</name>
				<t>
					In order for any multi-signer group to give consistent answers
					across all nameservers, the data contents of the zone also have to
					be synchronized (in addition to infrastructure records like NS,
					DNSKEY, CDS etc). This content synchronization is out-of-scope
					for this document.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>Terminology</name>
			<t>
				The key words "<strong>MUST</strong>", "<strong>MUST NOT</strong>",
				"<strong>REQUIRED</strong>", "<strong>SHALL</strong>", "<strong>SHALL NOT</strong>",
				"<strong>SHOULD</strong>", "<strong>SHOULD NOT</strong>",
				"<strong>RECOMMENDED</strong>", "<strong>MAY</strong>", and
				"<strong>OPTIONAL</strong>" in this document are to be interpreted as
				described in BCP 14	<xref target="RFC2119" /> <xref target="RFC8174" /> when,
				and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
			</t>
			<t><strong>Signer</strong></t>
			<t>An entity signing a zone</t>
			<t><strong>Multi-signer Group</strong></t>
			<t>A group of signers that sign the same zone</t>
			<t><strong>Controller</strong></t>
			<t>
				An entity controlling the multi-signer group. Used in
				the decentralized model.
			</t>
			<t><strong>Parent</strong></t>
			<t>See <xref target="RFC8499" /></t>
			<t><strong>Trust mechanism</strong></t>
			<t><strong>DS-Wait-Time</strong></t>
			<t>
				Once the parent has picked up and published the new DS record
				set, the any further changes MUST to be delayed until the
				new DS set has propagated.
			</t>
			<t>
				The minimum DS-Wait-Time is the TTL of the DS RRset.
			</t>
			<t><strong>DNSKEY-Wait-Time</strong></t>
			<t>
				Once the DNSKEY sets of all signers are updated, any further changes
				MUST to be delayed until the new DNSKEY set has propagated.
			</t>
			<t>
				The minimum DNSKEY-Wait-Time is the maximum of all DNSKEYS TTL
				values from all signers plus the time it takes to publish the zone on
				all secondaries.
			</t>
			<t><strong>NS-Wait-Time</strong></t>
			<t>
				Once the parent has picked up and published the new NS record set,
				any further changes MUST be delayed until the new NS set has
				propagated.
			</t>
			<t>
				The minimum NS-Wait-Time is the maximum of the TTL value of the
				NS set in the parent zone and all NS sets from all signers.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>Use Cases</name>
			<t>
				As described in <xref target="RFC8901" /> a multi-signer DNSSEC
				configuration has some challenges that can be overcome with the
				right infrastructure and following a number of steps for setup
				and operation.
			</t>
			<t>
				In this document we describe, except for the initial trust, how
				the steps in the multi-migner DNSSEC setup can be automated.
			</t>
			<section numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>Secure Nameserver Operator Transition</name>
				<t>
					Changing the nameserver operator of a DNSSEC signed zone can be
					challenging. Currently the most common method is temporarily
					"going insecure". This is poor for security, and for users
					relying on the security of the zone. Furthermore, when DNSSEC
					is being used for application security functions like DANE
					<xref target="RFC6698" />, it is critical that the DNSSEC chain
					of trust remain unbroken during the transfer.
				</t>
				<t>
					Multi-signer DNSSEC Model 2 provides a mechanism for transitioning
					from one nameserver operator to another without "going insecure".
					A new operator joins the current operator in a temporary
					multi-signer group. Once that is accomplished and stable the old
					operator leaves the multi-signer group completing the transition.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>Permanent multi-signer Operations</name>
				<t>
					Using multiple DNS providers to distribute authoritative DNS service
					with each provider signing independendly and with their own key set.
					This use-case is described in <xref target="RFC8901" />.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section anchor="automation" numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>Automation Models</name>
			<t>
				Automation of the necessary steps
				can be categorized into two main models, centralized and decentralized.
				Both have pros and cons, and a zone owner should carefully choose
                the model that works best.
			</t>
			<section anchor="centralized" numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>Centralized</name>
				<t>
					In a centralized model a controller executes all steps necessary
					and controls all signers.
				</t>
				<t>
					The controller needs to have authorized access to all signers.
					This can be achieved in a variety of different ways. For example will many
					service providers offer access through a REST API. Another possibility
					is access through Dynamic Update <xref target="RFC2136" /> with TSIG authentication.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section anchor="decentralized" numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>Decentralized</name>
				<t>
					In the decentralized models all signers will communicate with
					each other and execute the necessary steps on their instance
					only. For this signers need a specialized protocol to
					communicate configuration details that are not part of
					the zone data.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section anchor="capabilities" numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>Capabilities</name>
				<t>
					In order for any of the models to work the signer must
					support the following capabilities.
				</t>
				<ol>
					<li>Add DNSKEY records (without the private key)</li>
					<li>Remove (previously added) DNSKEY record(s)</li>
					<li>Add CDS and CDNSKEY records for keys not in the DNSKEY set</li>
					<li>Remove (previously added) CDS and CDNSKEY records</li>
					<li>Add CSYNC record</li>
					<li>Remove CSYNC record</li>
				</ol>
			</section>

		</section>
		<section anchor="algo" numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>Algorithms</name>
			<t>
				In a centralized model it is the controllers task to compute all waiting times and
				control the zone in a way that all timing restrictions are met.
			</t>
			<t>
				In the decentralized model every signer must compute all waiting times and adhere to
				all timing restrictions.
			</t>
			<t>
				In both methods it will be necessary that some of the timing restrictions must be given
				as part of the configuration data.
			</t>
			<section numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>Prerequisites</name>
				<t>Each signer to be added, including the initial signer, must
					meet the following prerequisites before joining the multi-signer
					Group
				</t>
				<ol>
					<li>
						A working setup of the zone, including DNSSEC signing.
					</li>
					<li>
						Uses the same algorithm for DNSSEC signing as the multi-signer
						group uses or will use.
					</li>
					<li>
						Signer or controller must be able to differentiate between its own keys and
						keys from others signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Signer or controller must be able to differentiate between NS records that
						are updated by itself and NS
						records that receive updates from other signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						If the domain is not covered by a CDS/CDNSKEY scanner and a
						CSYNC scanner updates to the parent zone have to be
						made manually.
					</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>Setting up a new multi-signer group</name>
				<t>
					The zone is already authoritatively served by one DNS operator and is DNSSEC signed.
					For full automation both the KSK and ZSK or CSK must be online.
				</t>
				<t>
					This would be a special case, a multi-signer group with only one signer.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>A signer joins the multi-signer group</name>
				<ol spacing="normal">
					<li>
						Confirm that the incoming signer meets the prerequisites.
					</li>
					<li>
						Establish a trust mechanism between the multi-signer group
						and the signer.
					</li>
					<li>
						Add ZSK for each signer to all other signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Calculate CDS/CDNSKEY Records for all KSKs/CSKs represented
						in the multi-signer group.
					</li>
					<li>
						Configure all signers with the compiled CDS/CDNSKEY RRSET.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait for Parent to publish the combined DS RRset.
					</li>
					<li>
						Remove CDS/CDNSKEY Records from all signers. (optional)
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait maximum of DS-Wait-Time and DNSKEY-Wait-Time
					</li>
					<li>
						Compile NS RRSET including all NS records from all
						signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Configure all signers with the compiled NS RRSET.
					</li>
					<li>
						Compare NS RRSET of the signers to the Parent, if there is a
						difference publish CSYNC record with NS and A and AAAA bit
						set on all signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait for Parent to publish NS.
					</li>
					<li>
						Remove CSYNC record from all signers. (optional)
					</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section numbered="true" toc="default">
				<name>A signer leaves the multi-signer group</name>
				<ol spacing="normal">
					<li>
						Remove exiting signer's NS records from remaining signers
					</li>
					<li>
						Compare NS RRSET of the signers to the Parent, if there
						is a difference publish CSYNC record with NS and A and AAAA
						bit set on remaining signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait for Parent to publish NS RRSET.
					</li>
					<li>
						Remove CSYNC record from all signers. (optional)
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait NS-Wait-Time
					</li>
					<li>
						Stop the exiting signer from answering queries.
					</li>
					<li>
						Calculate CDS/CDNSKEY Records for KSKs/CSKs published by
						the remaining signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Configure remaining signers with the compiled
						CDS/CDNSKEY RRSET.
					</li>
					<li>
						Remove ZSK/CSK of the exiting signer from remaining signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait for Parent to publish the updated DS RRset.
					</li>
					<li>
						Remove CDS/CDNSKEY set from all signers. (Optional)
					</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>A signer performs a ZSK rollover</name>
				<ol>
					<li>
						The signer introduces the new ZSK in its own DNSKEY RRset.
					</li>
					<li>
						Update all signers with the new ZSK.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait DNSKEY-Wait-Time
					</li>
					<li>
						Signer can start using the new ZSK.
					</li>
					<li>
						When the old ZSK is not used in any signatures by the signer,
						the signer can remove the old ZSK from its DNSKEY RRset.
					</li>
					<li>
						Remove ZSK from DNSKEY RRset of all signers.
					</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>A Signer performs a CSK or KSK rollover</name>
				<ol>
					<li>
						Signer publishes new CSK / KSK in its own DNSKEY RRset.
					</li>
					<li>
						In case of CSK, add CSK to DNSKEY set of all other signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Signer signs DNSKEY RRset with old and new CSK / KSK.
					</li>
					<li>
						Calculate new CDS/CDNSKEY RRset and publish on all signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait for parent to pickup and publish new DS RR set.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait DS-Wait-Time + DNSKEY-Wait-Time
					</li>
					<li>
						Signer removes old CSK/KSK from its DNSKEY RR set. And removes all
						signatures done with this key.
					</li>
					<li>
						In case  of CSK, remove old CSK from DNSKEY set of all other signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Calculate new CDS/CDNSKEY RRset and publish on all signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait for parent to pickup and publish new DS RR set.
					</li>
					<li>
						Remove CDS/CDNSKEY RR sets from all signers.
					</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Algorithm rollover for the whole multi-signer group</name>
				<ol>
					<li>All signers publish KSK and ZSK or CSK using the new algorithm.</li>
					<li>All signers sign all zone data with the new keys.</li>
					<li>Wait until all signers have signed all data with the new key(s).</li>
					<li>
						Add new ZSK of each signer to all other signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Calculate new CDS/CDNSKEY RRset and publish on all signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait for parent to pickup and publish new DS RR set.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait DS-Wait-Time + DNSKEY-Wait-Time
					</li>
					<li>
						Removes all keys and signatures which are using the old algorithm.
					</li>
					<li>
						Calculate new CDS/CDNSKEY RRset and publish on all signers.
					</li>
					<li>
						Wait for parent to pickup and publish new DS RR set.
					</li>
					<li>
						Remove CDS/CDNSKEY RR sets from all signers.
					</li>
				</ol>
			</section>
			<section>
				<name>Timing Considerations</name>
			</section>

		</section>
		<section>
			<name>Signers with different algorithms in a multi-signer group</name>
			<t>
				Only when all signers use the same algorithm(s) can all resolvers
				validate zone data with consistency.
			</t>
			<t>
				This section tries to summarize why that is the case and what trade-offs can be
				made in situations where using the same algorithm isn't possible.
			</t>
			<t>
				<xref target="RFC4035" section="2.2"/> states that
				a signed zone MUST include a DNSKEY for each algorithm present in
				the zone's DS RRset and expected trust anchors for the zone.
				A setup where different signers use different key algorithms therefore
				violates <xref target="RFC4035" />.
			</t>
			<t>
				According to <xref target="RFC6840" section="5.11" />
				validators SHOULD NOT insist that all algorithms signaled in the
				DS RRset work, and they MUST NOT insist that all algorithms signaled
				in the DNSKEY RRset work.
			</t>
			<t>
				So a multi-signer setup where different signers use different key
				algorithms should still validate.
			</t>
			<t>
				This could be an acceptable risk in a situation where going insecure
				is not desirable or impossible and name servers have to be changed
				between operators which only support distinct set of key algorithms.
			</t>
			<t>
				We have to consider the following scenarios:
			</t>
			<t><strong>Validator supports both algorithms</strong></t>
			<t>
				Validation should be stable through all stages of the multi-signer
				algorithms.
			</t>
			<t><strong>Validator supports none of the algorithms</strong></t>
			<t>
				The validator will treat the zone as unsigned. Resolution should
				work through all stages of the multi-signer algorithms.
			</t>
			<t><strong>Validator supports only one of the algorithms</strong></t>
			<t>
				The validator will not be able to validate the DNSKEY RR set or
				any data from one of the signers. So in some cases the validator
				will consider the zone bogus and reply with a SERVFAIL response code.
			</t>
			<t>
				The later scenario can be mitigated, but not fully eliminated, by
				selecting two well-supported algorithms.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>IANA Considerations</name>
			<t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>Security Considerations</name>
			<t>
			    multi-signer DNSSEC inherits the security considerations of <xref target="RFC7477" />, <xref target="RFC8078" /> and <xref target="RFC8901"/>.
			</t>
			<t>
				Every step of the multi-signer algorithms has to be carefully executed at the right time.
				Any failure could result in the loss of resolution for the domain.
			</t>
			<t>
				Independent of the chosen model, it is crucial that only authorized entities
				will be able to change the zone data. Some providers or software installation allow to
				make more specific configuration on the allowed changes. All extra steps to allow as little
				access to change zone data as possible should be taken.
			</t>
			<t>
				If used correctly, the multi-signer algorithm will strengthen the DNS security
				by avoiding "going insecure" at any stage of the domain life cycle.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="implementation" numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>Implementation Status</name>
			<t>
				One implementation of a centralized controller which supports updates
			  through Dynamic DNS or REST API's of several vendors has been implemented
				by the Swedish Internet Foundation.
			</t>
			<t>
				The code can be found as part of the multi-signer project on Github
				<eref target="https://github.com/DNSSEC-Provisioning/multi-signer-controller" />
			</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2136.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6840.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7477.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8078.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml"/>
		</references>
		<references title="Informative References">
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6698.xml"/>
			<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8901.xml"/>
		</references>

		<section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="true" toc="default">
			<name>Acknowledgements</name>
			<t>
				The authors would like to thank the following for their review of
				this work and their valuable comments: Steve Crocker, Eric Osterweil,
				Roger Murray, Jonas Andersson, Peter Thomassen.
			</t>
		</section>

	</back>
</rfc>
